## Tim Weigel

timweigel@gmail.com https://www.timweigel.dev https://www.linkedin.com/in/timothyweigel/

## **Profile**

I'm a skilled database administrator with database development experience. I'm enthusiastic, and a fast learner. I'm process-oriented, careful, methodical, and thorough. I ask questions when I need to, and my research skills are top-notch. I document my work. I'm an active part of the SQL Server community..

## Experience

DIGITAL OUTREACH COORDINATOR (VOLUNTEER), HOUSTON COUNTY ALABAMA DEMOCRATIC PARTY; DOTHAN, AL – APRIL 2020 - PRESENT

Actively developing a database for Party leadership to allow consolidation of disparate record-keeping systems into a single location. I conducted interviews with Party officials about their functional areas' requirements and data sources, and reviewed current document stores to determine what data exists within the Party's files and what will need to be gathered separately or sourced from other systems. I discussed budgetary constraints in concert with data volumes, access requirements, and desired reporting functionality to identify potential hosting providers. I am in the process of preparing an entity-relationship diagram to illustrate the data model I am developing.

Manage marketing platforms including creating and conducting campaigns via MailChimp, as well as overseeing Party Facebook and Twitter resources. Coordinate optiand options information with Party membership rolls.

Secure and maintain Party Google Drive and Gmail accounts.

SQL SERVER DBA, NATIONAL MULTIPLE SCLEROSIS SOCIETY; DENVER, CO (REMOTE) – MARCH 2018 - MAY 2020

Participated in requirements planning and vendor selection for the first phase of the Society's CRM transition to Salesforce's Nonprofit Success Pack. I collaborated closely with the selected vendor during the solution development, and wrote essential change tracking components to provide pertinent records for integration. Post-delivery I continued to collaborate closely with the integration specialist to expand integration functionality while refining and improving integration performance at the SQL Server and Dell Boomi layers.

Supported the Society's ERP migration from Epicor to Workday by migrating the legacy Epicor database into the Society's reporting infrastructure to facilitate the reporting and analytics team's goals.

Wrote the foundational documents of the cloud-first architecture plan to guide the Society's long-term data strategy. Advocated planned transitions from on-premises and laaS-based solutions to more scalable PaaS solutions for large-scale data storage, analytics, and data science, while recognizing platform gaps that require maintenance of traditional architecture for Master Data Management and legacy reporting functionality.

SENIOR DATABASE ADMINISTRATOR, PGI; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO – NOVEMBER 2016 - MARCH 2018

Developed a pilot program to upgrade the database platform from SQL Server 2008 to SQL Server 2014, including physical infrastructure upgrades, operating system upgrades from Windows Server 2008R2 to 2016, and SAN infrastructure upgrades for both primary production and disaster recovery and consolidations in collaboration with the storage administration and Windows administration teams.

Led multiple projects to improve SQL Server management, performance, and security. These entailed performing a comprehensive configuration review of all production SQL Server instances to identify and correct instances that were not configured according to corporate requirements, as well as conducting a security review of all production SQL Servers and implemented a plan to transition access from individual logins to Active Directory groups when appropriate.

Mentored junior DBAs. I helped them to plan work, expand their technical skills and operational knowledge, and develop into more rounded data professionals.

SQL SERVER DBA, NATIONAL MULTIPLE SCLEROSIS SOCIETY; DENVER, CO – MARCH 2016 - NOVEMBER

Played a key role in the Society's post-implementation transition from a hosted CRM platform to an internal CRM. This included standardizing database and platform operations in a DevOps model in collaboration with the application development and integration teams, as well as establishing policies and procedures for developing and implementing bug fixes and new features.

Standardized database platform operations, implementing best practices around backups, database maintenance, data security, and patching. As part of this I identified multiple

automated intrusion attempts and collaborated with the server and network administration teams to close attack vectors and harden the Society's database infrastructure.

SQL SERVER DBA, XTIVIA; COLORADO SPRINGS, CO - JULY 2015 - MARCH 2016

Provided wide-ranging SQL Server consulting and support services to a wide variety of clients ranging from small businesses to national organizations across a variety of sectors. I provided services such as data recovery, custom development, Analytics Platform Services implementations, and hosting assistance, as well as routine health checks and monitoring for new and established clients.

## Education

Colorado College, Colorado Springs, CO - BA Asian Studies, 2006 Graduated Cum Laude, recipient of the Excellence in Asian Studies award. Member of Phi Beta Kappa  $\beta$  of Colorado.

### Skills

SQL Server ecosystem administration, including backups, consistency checks, and index maintenance, SQL Server Integration Services and SQL Server Reporting Services management and troubleshooting, database planning and architecture, high-availability and disaster recovery planning and implementation including clustering, database replication, and performance monitoring and tuning

Windows Server administration, both physical and Azure Virtual Machine

Dell Boomi process development and maintenance

Business process development

Compliance audits

# SQL Server Community Involvement

WIREGRASS SQL & DATA COMMUNITY; DOTHAN, AL – 2020

I founded the Wiregrass SQL & Data Community in early 2020 to provide learning and networking opportunities to the underrepresented data community in the Wiregrass region encompassing Dothan, AL and surrounding counties.

As part of this, I secured PASS affiliation, meeting space through the Dothan Houston County Library System, set up social media accounts on Twitter, Facebook, and LinkedIn to conduct communication and marketing, and conducted marketing activities through various social media channels.

COLORADO SPRINGS SQL SERVER USERS GROUP: COLORADO SPRINGS, CO - 2016 - 2018

As Vice President of Membership from January 2017 to December 2018, I managed group membership and engaged in outreach activities to maintain and increase group membership.

As Vice President of Marketing from January 2016 to December 2016, I revived the group's dormant Twitter and Facebook accounts and implemented a social media strategy to increase group engagement. Coordinated email communication with group members about upcoming events and community news. Collaborated with our sponsors to ensure their messages reached our membership, leading to several staffing agencies increasing their sponsorship of our group.

I further assisted with planning and running multiple SQL Saturday events. Repeatedly succeeded in increasing the number of sponsors for the events, bringing new sponsors on board for 2016 and 2017. Participated in speaker vetting and selection, and event schedule planning. Coordinated volunteer engagement, overseeing volunteer staff. Participated actively in event setup and teardown.

#### **TALKS**

Change Tracking Methods in SQL Server

SQL Saturday Denver – September 2018 Denver SQL Server Users Group – April 2018 SQL Saturday Colorado Springs – March 2018

#### TempDB Management

Denver SQL Server Users Group – April 2017 Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group – February 2017

### Change Data Capture

MagicPASS (Remote, Orlando, FL) – April 2017 Colorado Springs SQL Server Users Group – September 2015

### Change Tracking

